WALTER WHEELER PAPERS (APAP212) 1977-2005
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Walter Wheeler Papers1977-2005
nam_apap212
This collection documents gay and lesbian publications with a particular emphasis on the Capital Region and Upstate New York. Material from New York City and neighboring states is also included.
Wheeler, Walter, 1977-2005
2.66
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Administrative History
The Correctional Association of New York was founded in 1844 by John W. Edmonds, President of the Board of Inspectors at Sing Sing Prison [Unless otherwise noted, all information is taken from The Correctional Association of New York, A History: 1844-1989]. Originally named the Prison Association of New York, the organization was formed to ameliorate the conditions of criminal defendants and prisoners, improve the discipline and administration of local jails and state prisons, and furnish assistance and encouragement to reformed convicts after discharge. It is the only private organization in the state that has the power to conduct on-site examinations of state and local correctional facilities and report its findings and recommendations to governmental authorities ["The Correctional Association of New York: A Public Interest Criminal Justice Membership Organization", in Resources Committee-Cocktail Part, 1982, folder, in Series 1, Board of Directors Files, 1942-88].
Since 1846, it has been charged with submitting an annual report on prison conditions in New York State to the New York State Assembly.
The Association has always furnished aid to male and female prisoners. However, roughly a decade after its foundation a number of members became convinced that the special needs of female offenders were not being addressed. Led by Issac G. Hopper, the chair of the Association's Female Department, they left the Association and formed their own group, the Women's Prison Association of New York ["Draft-Scope of the Association's Activities", circa 1975, in Correctional Association History, 1955-83, folder, in Series 1, Board of Directors Files, 1942-88. For more information about this organization, see: Women's Prison Association and Home, 150 Years in the Forefront: The Women's Prison Association and Home (1995). Available [online]: http://www.correctionhistory.org/html/chronicl/wpa/html/wpaopen.htm [13 April 2000]].
During the nineteenth century, the organization took a leading role in prison reform in the United States and the world. It formed the National Prison Association (now the American Prison Association), a nationwide umbrella organization, in 1870. Two years later, it started the International Prison Congress, a world-wide gathering of prison officials and social reformers that met every five years. The League of Nations eventually assumed responsibility for running the conferences, which are now held under the auspices of the United Nations.
The Association was active in promoting numerous criminal justice system reforms in New York State. The organization was instrumental in creating New York State's first probation and parole systems (c.1875) and pressed for the creation of separate facilities for youthful offenders (1864-74) and a separate juvenile justice system (1874-1904) ["A Brief Description of the Correctional Association's Purpose, History, Recent Publications, Current Program", in Correctional Association History, 1955-83, folder, in Series 1, Board of Directors Files, 1942-88, and untitled typescript notes beginning with "Parole/Probation", in Correctional Association History, 1955-83, folder, in Series 1, Board of Directors Files, 1942-88].
The Association sought to ensure that prisoners had opportunities to acquire formal education and advocated the creation of prison libaries (1904-24). It also fought to ensure that prisoners could learn a trade while incarcerated and that their labor was not exploited. Other policies the Association advocated included: a prison classification system; opposition to corporal punishment (1844-64); the Presidential Commutation Act; special care facilities for inmates afflicted with tuberculosis; establishment of a psychiatric clinic at Sing Sing Prison; creation of the New York City Parole Commission; establishment of prison libraries (1904-24); development of policies which enabled prisoners to contribute to the war effort by working in war-related industries (1940-42); establishment of a Crime Victims Compensation Board (1965-66); creation of an adequate public defender system [. The Prison Association of New York, One Hundred Years of Faithful Service, 1844-1944 (New York: The Prison Association of New York, 1944), 3-7. A copy of this publication is housed in the Correctional Association History, 1955-83, folder, in Series 1, Board of Directors Files, 1942-88].
In the 1960s and 1970s, the organization advocated the establishment of a Crime Victims Compensation Board (1965-66) and pressed for the decriminalization of pornography, sexual acts between consenting adults, and other crimes it deemed "victimless" ["Draft-Scope of the Association's Activities", circa 1975, in Correctional Association History, 1955-83, folder, in Series 1, Board of Directors Files, 1942-88].
Recent activities of the Association include the AIDS in Prison Project, the Public Policy Project, the Prison Overcrowding Project, the Prison and Jail Conditions Project, and the Prison Visiting Committee (1980-present). The Association has also been active in efforts to educate the public about the immense costs incurred by city, county, and state correctional agencies and to promote alternatives to incarceration for non-violent offenders ["The Correctional Association of New York: A Public Interest Criminal Justice Membership Organization"].
For more information about the Correctional Association and its history, visit http://www.correctionalassociation.org/ and http://www.correctionhistory.org/html/chronicl/cany/html/cany01.html.
Scope and Content Information
The publications range from professionally produced magazines to independently published zines. These publications are scheduled to be cataloged in Minerva, the University Libraries' online catalog. The collection also includes material often considered to be ephemeral such as handbills, flyers, advertising postcards, stickers, matchbooks, and other promotional material for various events and venues. Objects includes a condom packaged by the AIDS Council Project HOPE and a latex dental dam from the Women's Action Coalition both of which were used to promote safe sex.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has no series, arranged chronologically.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives by Walter Wheeler. 2005 December
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Subject and Genre Headings
Human Sexuality and Gender Identity; Wheeler, Walter; Gay activists--Periodicals.; journals (periodicals)
Container List
- ACT (Albany Civic Theater), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- A.L.Y.S.O.N., 1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- ASP (Albany Student Press), 2000-2001 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Amfar-AIDS Research, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- A&U, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- A&U, 1993; 1997 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- A&U, 1998; 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Bay Windows, 1986; 1997 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Bay Window, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bi Notes, 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Capital Pride, 2001; 2005 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- CDC (Centers for Disease Control), Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Center Happenings, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Community, 1989-1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Community, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Community, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Community, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Community, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Community, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Community, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Community, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Community, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- CommUnity, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- CommUnity, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- CommUnity, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- CommUnity, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- CommUnity, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- CommUnity, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Each of Us Inevitable, 1977-1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Farm, Undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- The Fifty Column, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Gay Community News, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Gaynet, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Gayzette, Greater Utica Lambda Foundation (GULF), 1991; 1994-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- GLBT-New Englands largest newspaper, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- The Griot Press, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Human Rights Campaign, 1997; 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Hurricane Girl, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Hx, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- In Our Own Voices, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- In the Life-The Lesbian & Gay Newspaper of the Hudson Valley & Tri-State Area, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- In the Life -The Lesbian & Gay Newspaper of the Hudson Valley & Tri-State Area, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- In the Life - The Lesbian & Gay Newspaper of the Hudson Valley & Tri-State Area, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- In the Life - The Lesbian & Gay Newspaper of the Hudson Valley & Tri-State Area, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- In the Life - The Lesbian & Gay Newspaper of the Hudson Valley & Tri-State Area, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- In the Life - The Lesbian & Gay Newspaper of the Hudson Valley & Tri-State Area, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- In the Life - The Lesbian & Gay Newspaper of the Hudson Valley & Tri-State Area, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- In the Life - The Lesbian & Gay Newspaper of the Hudson Valley & Tri-State Area, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Inside Out Hudson Valley, 2004-2005 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Inside Out Hudson Valley, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Lambda Rising News, 1994-1995 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- The Lesbian and Gay Pink Pages, Gay Pride Issue, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Lesbians, Gays, and Bisexuals Newsweekly Au Courant, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- LGNY (Lesbian & Gays New York), 1997 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Love and Rage, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Men Talk, Twin Cities Mens Center, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Metroland, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Metroline, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Metroline, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Metropolitan Community Church of the Hudson Valley, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Next, 1996; 1999 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Northeast Magazine, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- One in Ten, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Out & About, Undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Out in the Mountains, 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- People First, Rensselar Polytechnic Institute, Undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
- PFLAG Pole, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- The Pink Paper, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Positive Images, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- PWAlive, Newsletter by, for, and about People affected by AIDS, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- QNortheast, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Queer Ramblings, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Sapphos Isle, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- To Avoid Suffocation, Gull, #1-4, Undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Two Rivers, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Venus, Undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
- 1. Womens Building News, (Albany), 1994-1996 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Womens Building News, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Flyers, Handbills, Postcards, and Related Material, 1985-2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Stickers, 1985-1995 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Womens Action Coalition, Latex Dam, 1985-1995 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Inside Out Hudson Valley, Matchbook, 1995-2005 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- AIDS Council Project HOPE, Condom, 19954-2005 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- ACT-UP!, Posters, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Our Town, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- The Source, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)